{
  "category": "Programming Languages",
  "difficulty": "easy",
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following programming languages is an object-oriented language developed by James Gosling at Sun Microsystems?",
      "options": [
        "Java",
        "Python",
        "C++",
        "JavaScript"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Java",
      "id": "EA5E20E0-A86C-4273-A5B6-B376D7F2BB66"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which programming language was created by Guido van Rossum and emphasizes code readability?",
      "options": [
        "Ruby",
        "Java",
        "Python",
        "C"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Python",
      "id": "DA2179E4-0D9E-4339-A662-7A6BCB5DF824"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a popular language for web development and often runs on the server-side?",
      "options": [
        "C",
        "Scala",
        "PHP",
        "Swift"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "PHP",
      "id": "4C48C810-4A4B-4653-AF67-C3C5CF12728A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which programming language is primarily used for iOS and macOS app development?",
      "options": [
        "Kotlin",
        "Swift",
        "Haskell",
        "Rust"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Swift",
      "id": "2588D47E-2B9E-4DF5-9D6A-7AFF4DD6CE48"
    },
    {
      "question": "What language was developed by Microsoft and is commonly used for Windows application development?",
      "options": [
        "Java",
        "C#",
        "Python",
        "C++"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "C#",
      "id": "32CAD75B-1761-4DC2-B410-7C326B4AD7A3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following languages is a superset of JavaScript and adds optional static typing?",
      "options": [
        "TypeScript",
        "CoffeeScript",
        "Dart",
        "Python"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "TypeScript",
      "id": "CA6A58BB-73D5-4D49-B822-4C79E17E0B79"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following languages is commonly used for creating web page interactivity and is executed on the client-side?",
      "options": [
        "Python",
        "Java",
        "C++",
        "JavaScript"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "JavaScript",
      "id": "4BFE6618-CAAE-4BDB-A0E8-3644F9B332DA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which programming language was developed by Yukihiro Matsumoto and is often used for web development?",
      "options": [
        "Python",
        "Ruby",
        "Perl",
        "PHP"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ruby",
      "id": "008B7E0E-6BB3-47BF-B283-E756796B9924"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following languages is a functional programming language, particularly popular for concurrent programming and distributed systems?",
      "options": [
        "Erlang",
        "Go",
        "Objective-C",
        "Rust"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Erlang",
      "id": "05DEDA01-4B70-42D9-83B9-3216E0AFFF80"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which programming language, developed by Google, is known for its simplicity and efficient performance, often used in systems programming and server side applications?",
      "options": [
        "Kotlin",
        "Go",
        "Dart",
        "Rust"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Go",
      "id": "B4567DA2-A0FE-46C1-B958-03F114685A95"
    }
  ]
}
